{"tossups": [{"question": "Tacitus recorded that, before this leader\u2019s uprising, a statue of Victory fell down, as if turning its back in retreat. Due to the Roman governor\u2019s absence at Mona, this leader trounced the Ninth Legion and destroyed a temple dedicated to Claudius. Suetonius defeated this ruler\u2019s forces at the Battle of Watling Street. Camulodunum and Londinium were destroyed by an army of Britons led by, for ten points, what British warrior queen of the Iceni?", "answer": "<b> Boudica</b> (accept<b> Boadicea</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "One author in this language wrote of a woman whose royal husband communicates with her using a medium after she is killed by soldiers in \u201cThe Song of Everlasting Sorrow.\u201d One author in this language wrote of the \u201crumble-rumble of war chariots\u201d in a poem bemoaning the An Lushan Rebellion. This language was used to write \u201cDrinking Alone By Moonlight\u201d the most noted poem of Li Po. For ten points, name this language in which poets like Bai Juyi and Wang Wei wrote under the Tang Dynasty.", "answer": "Middle<b> Chinese</b> (accept<b> Mandarin</b>)", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "During this battle, one side could not move to Gloucester Point due to a storm and could not evacuate at all after the Battle of the Chesapeake. According to legend, ceremonies after this battle featured the losers playing \u201cThe World Turned Upside Down.\u201d Redoubts 9 and 10 were captured during this siege, which was led by the Comte de Rochambeau and George Washington against forces under Charles Cornwallis. For ten points, name this decisive battle of the American Revolution at which the British army surrendered.", "answer": "Battle (or Siege) of<b> Yorktown</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This battle was preceded by an engagement at Flirey that allowed one side to take control of local railway lines. Fort Vaux and Douamount were heavily contested in this battle. Erich von Falkenhayn was dismissed for failing to win this battle, despite his boast that he would bleed his enemies white. Philippe Petain led French troops to victory in, for ten points, what lengthy 1916 battle for a French fortress city?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Verdun</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This position was to be revered, and the barbarians were to be expelled, according to the slogan \u201cSonno Joi.\u201d Scholars and politicians have debated whether the song \u201cKimigayo\u201d celebrates this figure. Under the Insei, the holder of this position retired to become a Buddhist monk but still held power as a Joko. According to legend, Jimmu was the first holder of this position, whose holders are given a posthumous name reflecting the era in which they ruled. For ten points, what ruler sits on the Chrysanthemum Throne as the leader of an East Asian country?", "answer": "<b> Emperor</b> of<b> Japan</b> (accept<b> Tenno</b>; accept<b> Mikado</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Bernie Boston was nominated for a Pulitzer Prize for a photo at this location showing a man putting a flower in the barrel of a gun. A set of documents named for this complex were leaked by Daniel Ellsberg and detailed American involvement in Vietnam. A conspiracy theory about this location holds that it was hit by a cruise missile, not an airplane, on September 11th. Arlington County, Virginia is home to, for ten points, what largest office building in the world, the headquarters of the US Department of Defense?", "answer": "The<b> Pentagon</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This US state was first formally claimed by Commodore John D. Sloat, who became its first military governor. After the city of Sonoma in this state was seized by the forces of William Ide and John C. Fremont, it briefly became its own republic. This site of the Bear Flag Revolt received a massive influx of settlers called \u201cforty-niners\u201d after a valuable commodity was discovered at Sutter\u2019s Mill. For ten points, name this state that underwent a massive gold rush in 1848.", "answer": "<b> California</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This leader\u2019s son dismissed pogroms after this leader\u2019s death with the line \u201cwhen a great tree falls, the earth shakes.\u201d This leader used a slogan translating as \u201cabolish poverty, rescue the country\u201d and launched Operation Blue Star against the Golden Temple at Amritsar, leading to her assassination by her own bodyguards. After her death, this leader\u2019s post was taken by her son, Rajiv. For ten points, name this first female Prime Minister of India.", "answer": "<b> I</b>ndira<b> Gandhi</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "During this ruler\u2019s coronation, a stampede led to the death of over a thousand people in the Khodynka Field tragedy. This man lost popularity after his forces opened fire on Father Gapon\u2019s supporters outside the Winter Palace. After this ruler abdicated, he and his family were brought to Yekaterinburg, where they were executed in July 1918. The February Revolution ousted, for ten points, what final Tsar of Russia?", "answer": "<b> Nicholas II</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The Wielbark culture of these people is the subject of<em> Getica</em>, a work by Jordanes. Emperor Valens died fighting these people, who were led by Fritigern, at the Battle of Adrianople. The 410 Sack of Rome was caused by Alaric, a leader of these people. Theodoric the Great led a kingdom of these people in Italy, while another group settled in Spain south of the Franks. For ten points, name this Germanic group that was split into Visi- and Ostro- branches.", "answer": "<b> Goth</b>s (accept<b> Visigoth</b>s and/or<b> Ostrogoth</b>s)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>During World War II, this country was led by the military dictator Phibun. This country has been ruled by the Chakri Dynasty since the death of its King Taksin the Great. This</b> <b>country\u2019s monarchs traditionally take the name (+)</b> <b>\u201cRama,\u201d and before the founding of</b> <b>this country\u2019s current capital, ruled from cities such as Ayutthaya and (*)</b> Sukhothai. For ten points, name this Southeast Asian country where a 2004 coup d\u2019etat forced Thaksin Shinawatra out of power in Bangkok.", "answer": "<b> Thailand</b> (accept<b> Siam</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This US state welcomed the von Trapp family singers to its city of Stowe after they fled Austria. This state celebrates an annual holiday on August 16th to commemorate the Battle of Bennington, which was fought in 1777 after it formed a (+) republic that lasted until it became the fourteenth state in 1791. Lake (*)</b> Champlain forms part of the western border of this state, which contains the headquarters of Ben & Jerry\u2019s in its city of Burlington. For ten points, name this state that once broke away from its eastern neighbor, New Hampshire.", "answer": "<b> Vermont</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Settlements in this modern-day country included one ruled by the tyrant Telys, Sybaris, which was conquered by Croton. Magna Graecia lies in this modern-day country, where the (+) Pyrrhic War took place. Nicias and Alcibiades led a failed expedition to an island now owned by this country. The (*)</b> Appian Way lies in this country, the ancient home of the Etruscans. For ten points, name this European country where tourists can visit ruins of the Circus Maximus and Colosseum in Rome.", "answer": "<b> Italy</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Black Kettle was killed at the Battle of the Washita River by this man\u2019s (*)</b> 7th Cavalry, which was wiped out in 1876 during the Great Sioux [soo] War. For ten points, name this US Army officer whose death at the Battle of the Little Bighorn led it to be known as his \u201cLast Stand.\u201d", "answer": "George Armstrong<b> Custer</b> Page 9", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Although lawyers debated whether this man owned a rare pair of Bruno Magli shoes, a photograph that was published in the</b><em><b> National Enquirer</b></em><b> supposedly showing him wearing</b> <b>the shoes was not entered into evidence. This man, who was arrested after a (+)</b> <b>sports</b> <b>memorabilia robbery at the Palace Station casino in Las Vegas, was defended by Johnnie (*)</b> Cochran and Robert Kardashian in an earlier trial concerning the deaths of Ron Goldman and Nicole Brown. For ten points, name this NFL running back who was acquitted of murder in a massive 1995 trial.", "answer": "Orenthal James \u201cOJ\u201d<b> Simpson</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This thinker controversially proposed that the inherent value of a commodity consisted of its labor value in a work that criticized what he called \u201ccommodity fetishism.\u201d This man theorized an explanation of history in which societies move through an industrial (+) capitalist stage to a final socialist society. This man declared that \u201cthe history of the world is a history of (*) </b> class struggle\u201d in a work that begins \u201ca spectre is haunting Europe\u201d and was co-written with Friedrich Engels. For ten points, name this author of<em> Das Kapital</em> and co-author of<em> The</em> <em>Communist Manifesto</em>.", "answer": "Karl<b> Marx</b> ", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b>Citizens of this empire referred to it as Tawantinsuyu. This empire was undergoing</b> <b>the War of the Two Brothers when it was invaded by a conquering force. The death</b> <b>of (+)</b> <b>Huayna Capac led to that succession war between his sons Hu\u00b4ascar and</b> <b>Atahualpa. This empire, whose main language was Quechua, had its capital at (*)</b> Cusco. Francisco Pizarro led 180 Spanish soldiers in victory over, for ten points, what American empire that built Machu Picchu and ruled a large empire in the Andes in the 15th and 16th centuries?", "answer": "<b> Inca</b>n Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}